<b>Ember's Lute - FAQ and Troubleshooting</b>
<br><br>
This book is a compilation of frequently asked questions and common troubleshooting issues with both this mod and with BG3 modding in general, as of January 2025. Happily for us, Larian are still patching and updating BG3 regularly, some 18 months after its release. This also means some of the troubleshooting referenced in this guide may become less relevant over time. Keep in mind when reviewing this in-game book for advice. 
<br><br>
You'll find more up to date and comprehensive guides on both the mod.io page (https://mod.io/g/baldursgate3/m/na110901) and the Nexusmods page (https://www.nexusmods.com/baldursgate3/mods/9678) for this mod and its dependendents.
<br><br>
<b>The Mod Won't Update</b>
<br><br>
Issues relating to updating mods are most commonly experienced by players on Windows who are using the in-game Mod Manager. There are a couple of ways it presents, such as a Blue update arrow that doesn't disappear, or a Windows error is thrown with a locked file message. 
<br><br>
The <b>locked file</b> issue was caused by earlier versions of this mod that contained virtual textures, for which there is a reported BG3 bug that locks the mod if it is enabled when you start BG3. If you see the locked error when attempting an update of the mod, then disable the mod (do not unsubscribe, just uncheck the box) and restart BG3. With the mod disabled, you should now be able to update it to the latest version and then re-enable it to start your Save game.
<br><br>
The <b>persistent blue arrow<b> is someties a result of the BG3 Mod Manager becoming out of sync with mod.io. It may require you to follow the same steps as for the locked file issue (disable the mod, restart BG3). Once back in the Mod Manager, Unsubscribe from the affected mod and then exit BG3. Check your Mods folder in Windows Explorer and make sure there are no other versions of the mod left in the folder. If you find any, delete them all manually. Now launch BG3 again. BG3 may automatically download the latest version of the mod, but if not, go to the Mod Manager and re-download again. You should now have the latest version installed and enabled.
<br><br>
<b>The Mod Won't Unsubscribe</b>
<br><br>
This issue is usually the same root cause as the update issues: either a locking file or a sync issue with mod.io. Follow the steps for the answer above and adjust the final steps to unsubscribe rather than update or re-download the mod.
<br><br>
<b>There Are No Crowd Reactions for Music Performances</b>
<br><br>
This is a symptom of a common way BG3 mods can inadvertently break the brittle BG3 music performance system in game. None of the Ember's Lute music mods cause this bug! Ironically, perhaps, but music mod authors are more likely to test music performances, be aware of the brittle nature of the way music statuses have been implemented in the base game, and correct for it. Unfortunately, it is very easy for any other mod (especially those that seemingly have nothing to do with music or the bard class) to inadvertently break music performances and crowd reactions.
<br><br>
If you do have another mod installed which is causing this bug then the other symptom you will observe is that playing music on a vanilla instrument will be interrupted after a few seconds. The reason custom instruments in this mod are not interrupted is because they do not use the vanilla game custom music statuses (except for crowd reactions - which are affected).
<br><br>
Unfortunately, unless you are on Windows and comfortable reading logs, there is no easy means to identify which mod is causing the interruptions, other than trial and error (adding mods in one by one until the interruptions can be replicated). It is unlikely to be a cosmetic mod. Framework mods, or those that add complex new spells may be the place to begin if you are considering this approach.
<br><br>
If you are a <b>Windows user</b>, then you can try installing the Optional Files mod "musicperformanceworkaround" from the Ember's Lute Nexusmods page: https://www.nexusmods.com/baldursgate3/mods/9678?tab=files instead. You may need to experiment with Load Order, but sometimes this mod can prevent the interruptions. It is a simple override mod, and is safe to be added or removed at any point in your campaign, so it is straightforward to try at least and see if it helps.
<br><br>
Finally, here's a link to an article on this common issue with a bit more information: https://www.nexusmods.com/baldursgate3/articles/796. For the record, you can also see the interrupting issue occur in an unmodded version of BG3, albeit less impactful. But in case you're interested, then here's how it is reproduced: any character with an aura up (such as the Paladin auras), can cancel down music performances by walking into closer range of the music performer. Once the aura status is applied to the performer, the music is cancelled and the performance stops.
<br><br>
<b>How Do I Uninstall this Mod?</b>
<br><br>
This answer assumes "uninstall" means to erase the mod from a Save campaign. See the answer above for an issue related to "Unsubscribing" the mod via the BG3 Mod Manager.
<br><br>
For console users: Once you Save your campaign with a mod enabled, BG3 will require the mod to be active and enabled from that Save point onwards in the campaign. In order to continue the campaign after removing this mod via the in-game Mod Manager, you will need to load a Save game from before this mod was added. I therefore recommend that you trial this mod and decide whether you wish to keep it in your campaign before progressing several hours further into the story.
<br><br>
For Windows users: Once you Save your campaign with a mod enabled that adds custom items, statuses, etc., then pre-requisite steps in-game are required in order to remove the mod. This typically involves erasing the custom items and statuses (please note it is not enough to simply sell them to a vendor - the items must be fully erased). The easiest way to achieve this is with Volitio's Mod Uninstaller on Nexusmods https://www.nexusmods.com/baldursgate3/mods/9701. This mod requires Script Extender and a couple of other dependencies, so see the author's mod page for more information.
<br><br>
Alternatively, if you have been keeping careful track of your custom items for this mod, then you may be able to manually erase the items with a little bit of in-game trickery.
<br><br> 
Use a custom Ember's Lute instrument to summon the Tiefling Spirit. Pick-pocket the Tiefling, and move <b>ALL</b> of the custom mod items (including containers, books, instruments, pieces of clothing, everything) into her inventory. 
<br><br>
Once you think you've got everything, have the tiefling dismiss herslf. This should result in all the custom items in her inventory disappearing with her. 
<br><br>
Next, take a Long Rest. This action should clear down any temporary custom statuses as well as reset the Vendor trade inventories. 
<br><br>
Save the game. Uninstall the mod. 
<br><br>
Restart BG3 and try to load your game. If you were successful in tracking down all the custom items, then you'll still need to accept a warning about a missing mod, but you will get back into the game OK. If it crashes you back to the Main Menu, then unfortunately it did not work and there are still custom items or statuses that need erasing. You will have to reinstall the mod and try again. Make sure to check your Camp Chest, companion equipment slots, etc.
<br><br>
<b>My Question Isn't Answered Here</b>
<br><br>
BG3 has an in-game feature which allows the reporting of mod issues. Please be aware that if you use this reporting feature, then you must provide as much information about the issue as possible in the report. The issue reporting itself is currently bugged until Larian or mod.io fix it. Mod authors are not able to reply to issue reports by users or request more information and all user reports come through anonymously.
<br><br>
Until the reporting feature is fixed, then the best place to raise issues or ask questions is on the Nexusmods page for Ember's Lute. https://www.nexusmods.com/baldursgate3/articles/796. For general questions, mod.io page is also fine https://mod.io/g/baldursgate3/m/na110901, though not the easiest format for troubleshooting back and forth.



